what is Pripco and what problem are you looking at solving with this company?
Well, thank you for having me today. That's a great question to start. So with Pripco,
we are one of the largest prop tech platforms in the MENA region. And today we're focused on
two areas, which is financing. So we do mortgages. We're partnered with more than 18 leading banks
in the country. And we do almost a billion that comes off mortgages a month. And so that's a heavy
focus for us. And then the second focus for us is fractional ownership, where we do fraction
ownership. We are regulated by the DFSA. And we have our platform Pripco blocks. And then we
recently launched Pripco Mint, which is our tokenization platform. So I want to talk about that for
income of tokenized ownership. Obviously, we used to call this security tokens. It's been around
for us sometime. The big challenge you always had was liquidity. How do you see the being able
to address this liquidity issue when it comes to a fractional ownership or tokenized assets?
Look, liquidity in real estate is relatively easier than other real world assets because it's
yielding an actual dividend or an actual rental yield in this case. And so the liquidity is looked
at in terms of a bigger pool of potential investors that are looking for a fixed
yield that's paid monthly, quarterly, annually. Today with interest rates going down and on a trend
to be lowered and lowered, it's a very attractive asset for somebody to own where they know that
they're making something on a monthly basis. And they also have the upside of capital appreciation,
the exposure to the market. And Dubai has become somewhere that everybody wants to be part of the
story, part of the journey. And so it's a great opportunity to allow that from a lower entry
cost into the market and to allow more of an audience to participate in the exposure of the market.
You know, as an end user, I hate the user experience of buying property. You know, there's the agents,
the mortgages, the whole experience is not very user friendly. You believe with tokenization,
obviously, what's happening on fractionalization, but also everything on the financing side,
the UX UI of buying at least stake in a property will change over the next couple of years.
Definitely. I think it'll become a lot more transparent, a lot more efficient,
very fast and very easy. Today you can buy property within three to five minutes on our platform.
And it will still include all parties. The banks will still be included from a financing perspective.
The brokers will still be included from an acquisition and sale of those properties
as a whole property perspective. But the platform will make it a lot more uniform on
bringing all of these parties together. And not just our platform, but the ecosystem of
PropTech and where it's headed in the next few years, sorry. And Dubai is very keen on that. I
think they're looking to make it as efficient as possible and has a big focus on PropTech as a
sector. Well, you know, recently we had in Dubai where the Dubai Land Department, the land titles
per se were put on chain, which is different than normally traditionally when we talk about
real estate tokenization. We used to tokenize SPV that is holding those assets. What is the
importance of the land titles themselves being put on the blockchain compared to the other model?
I think it's a phenomenal initiative. It provides a lot more transparency and
credibility for the government to be involved for the Dubai Land Department to be leading the space
and to be offering that in collaboration to achieve the wider market accessibility to real estate.
And so they've done a phenomenal job. They have pioneered innovation globally and in the
MENA in terms of being at the forefront of this as an initiative and as a concept. And it's been
extremely innovative and they've been phenomenal. I think it's a use case is absolutely fantastic
on this side. And you know, when you look at outside of Dubai or the UAE and you look about
everything happening, there is possible now on tokenization and the financing angle as well,
where do you see are the next markets where this could work very well? I think ultimately
in general tokenization, whether real estate or other asset classes, is something that will become
extremely common across many different markets because it gives access to assets across different
demographics and different entry points. So I think it will become something that's more globally
accepted and globally received well across different asset classes. I don't think it will be limited
to one or two or three geographies. And I think it will be across everything. They've already
started doing it very heavily into gold, silver, you know, Robinhood recently announced tokenization
into private markets and private companies. And so I think it'll become something that goes across
every touch point. And if anything can be sold as a full asset, it should be able to be sold as a
tokenized fractional asset on a chain. I think many believe that actually the entire financial
markets and we're seeing it now with treasuries actually and the increased rise we've seen on
tokenized assets. One thing as CEO of the company, when you look at this, what is the biggest risk
that you see with the rise of tokenized assets? Is there a particular risk you see is different
than what we have with physical old school real estate assets? That's a good question. I don't see
a specific risk to do with that differentiates from the old school assets. I think whatever risk
comes with a specific asset class is the risk you're taking in that asset class. So as an example,
if you're buying gold today, whether you're buying, you know, full kilo of gold or tokenized fractional,
you know, small amount of gold, your risk is gold. Your risk is not the process or the, you know,
ability to fractionalize it or tokenize it. The risk itself is associated with the asset class.
I think if you were to ask me what is potentially the biggest risk in it as tokenization or fraction
ownership across any asset class, I think it would be the education curve that needs to be focused on
so that people understand the risks associated with that asset class, whether you're investing
a hundred dollar hums, a hundred dollars, a million dollars or a hundred million dollars.
I think the education curve needs to be there in order for them to understand what are they
investing in, why are they investing in it, what is their expected return from this investment?
It's a problem I think we see across the crypto ecosystem, the lack of education in this space is
a big one. For sure, but you know, I think that is on par today with the equity market in terms of
just a lot more people are becoming investors in the market, which is great. I think it's
also the generation is more focused on investment, you know, wanting to put their money to work.
And so being at the forefront of education is actually a great place to be. You want to be able
to contribute to the education of a sector and the education of an investment, you know,
pool and criteria before people go into it. And I remember you mentioned a point that
generational issue, you know, like you see in your users you have right now, a certain particular
type of client is an age group is a younger people are using and compared to older ones.
The predominant age group we see is between 20 to 45. And I think that's more to do not
with the investment itself of an asset class, but the usage of technology. I think obviously the
younger generation is more comfortable with investing their money through technology and through
platforms where they can, you know, read up, understand the risks, the KYC and the methodology
of investing. It doesn't mean that the older or younger generation is alienated. I think it's
just a matter of comfort. I think for some people, you know, that are off the older generation they
still prefer to, you know, meet somebody before making an investment, have a person in front of
them. It's not as digitized as it could be. And that's okay. I think it's just a demographic
thing. It's what you're comfortable with. And I think country by country that differs.
So I think in the MENA region actually we're a lot more far ahead at the diversity of age range
in terms of investors. And in some countries you see it skew more towards older, some are
younger. So I think it depends on the demographic you're looking at.
Very interesting. I'd love to have you back in a couple of years here to see actually how
Proptych has evolved on that perspective. That was Amiro Sashawani, the founder and CEO, Pripco.